Britain's major galleries house some of
the finest collections of art to be
found anywhere in the world.
>> But there are thousands [music] of other
artworks we know little about in the
collections of smaller institutions.
Over 80% of this publicly owned treasure
is in storage and often uncataloged. We
don't know the name of the artist, the
subject, or when and where they were
painted.
>> The Art UK website was created to shine
a light into these shadows and now has
over 200,000 paintings online.
Using this database, we'll be traveling
the country seeking out potential lost
masterpieces.
>> When we find an interesting painting,
I'll [music] investigate the story
behind its creation using a meticulous
process of restoration, research, and
scientific analysis.
>> I'll be exploring the world in which
these works were created, the social and
historical background to the life of the
artists, which gives a painting its
context. But simply finding a painting
is just the beginning of the trail.
>> This week we've come to Oxford to
uncover the story behind a portrait of a
student who took his degree in 1745.
>> This is this is really good.
>> He studied medicine [music] at a time
when advances in the science of human
anatomy relied on cutting up the
cadavers of condemned murderers.
>> To be publicly anatomized.
That was utter humiliation.
>> I think the picture might have been
painted in Rome by one of the greatest
portraitists in art history.
>> In Rome, the first thing they did was
head to the tailor. Next thing they went
to the portrait painter.
>> Today, it's in the collection of the
Bodleian Library Oxford.
I'll be looking into the extraordinary
history of this institution, which now
receives a thousand books a day.
>> We have 153 miles [music] worth of
storage.
>> In order to prove my hunch about the
portrait, I need to persuade the
Bodleian Library to let me borrow a
painting instead of a book.
>> You do know that you're not allowed to
borrow the books anyway.
>> Oh really?
>> I'm afraid so. In 1645, even Charles I
had his request denied.
>> What did he want to borrow?
>> Well, funnily enough, it was a history
of the world. Imagine what he might have
learned if they could have just relaxed
the rules a little.
>> Looking after us for our visit is Dana
Josephson.
>> How do you do?
>> Very well, thanks.
>> Good. How do you do?
Dana has been cataloging the Bodleian's
extensive art collection.
And he's agreed to show me around the
reading rooms, where the pictures hang.
Looking through Art UK, there are about
320 paintings in the Bodleian's
collection, and almost every single one
is a portrait. Mostly of very
learned-looking scholars.
>> [music]
>> But one of these, a picture of a certain
George [music] Oakley Aldridge, caught
my attention online, as it looks to be
very finely painted. A cut above the
rest, and a potential overlooked gem.
George has been moved out of the reading
rooms to the Bodleian Conservation
Studio, where I can get a good look at
him without disturbing anyone.
>> So there he is.
>> Found him. Thank you.
>> I'll leave you to it.
>> Okay, thanks.
>> [music]
>> Well, I thought this looked good on the
Art UK website, where it carried my
favorite attribution, unknown artist.
But in the flesh, what a superlative
piece of painting.
I think this is by an Italian artist
called Pompeo Batoni, who was not only
the owner of one of the finest names in
art history, but one of the best
portrait painters who ever lived.
In his prime, Batoni was patronized by
emperors, queens, and popes, but he was
particularly beloved by the British. And
of the over 225 portraits that he
thought to have painted throughout his
life, 175 of them are of British
subjects. There's barely a stately home
in Britain that doesn't have one of
Pompeo Batoni's pictures on its walls.
Now, what do the Brits love about a
Batoni portrait? Well, first of all, he
was excellent doing that hyper-real
detail, things like the fur in the hat
and the the bright colors of the
costume. And that helps make you look
rich and important. But Batoni also adds
an element of spontaneity and
characterization that few portraitists
have ever achieved. And that's why
Aldrich's face here looks so animated.
His lips are pursed. He's about to
embrace us in conversation, to say
something witty and urbane.
It's suffering from a a layer of dirt
and old varnish, which is slightly
flattening the image. And there's a
slight area here where it looks like
some cheeky student has flicked his
fountain pen, but very excited as to
what this might reveal. It could be a
really, really important painting.
>> While Bendor has been looking at the
picture collection, I've been looking
into the history of the Bodleian
Library.
The first purpose-built reading room was
in this church, St. Mary's on the High
Street, and it quickly became the
nucleus of the university.
>> Being handwritten by scribes, the books
that were kept here would have been
extremely valuable, and consequently not
that numerous. In fact, the library
probably only had about 20 books, and
these would have been kept chained to
the walls.
>> 100 years [music] later, with the
invention of the printing press, books
suddenly became cheaper and consequently
more numerous.
>> Shortly after that, for the first, but
I'm sure not the last time somebody
said, "You're going to need a bigger
library."
At the time, England was in the depths
of the 100 Years War with France, and
had lost a large portion of her
population to the Black Death.
But, it was also a period when the arts
and crafts flourished.
In 1447, when Humphrey, Duke of
Gloucester, gave the university his
collection of 280 books,
this was the room they built to house
them.
This was the first library [music] in
England to have shelves along the walls,
becoming the inspiration for all
libraries since.
Duke Humphrey's collection lasted only
60 years, though.
In 1550, in an anti-Catholic purge, the
books were burnt, and the room became
part of the medical school.
It would be another 50 years before the
university replaced its library, and it
was thanks to the efforts of a former
fellow of Merton College, Thomas Bodley.
Bodley, who gave his name to the
library, refurbished the existing rooms
and built elegant new ones. But, it
didn't come cheap.
I absolutely love the fact that Thomas
owed his fortune, and Oxford its
library, to this, pilchards.
Now, Thomas wasn't a particularly
wealthy man, but he had married a very
rich widow, whose husband had made his
fortune trading in pilchards.
When Thomas retired, he devoted the
pilchard fortune to giving Oxford back a
library.
The Bodleian Library opened in 1602 with
2,500 books. But, perhaps the most
significant event in the library's
history took place [music] a few years
later in 1610.
Bodley entered into an arrangement with
the Stationers' Hall in London that was
to profoundly affect the future of his
new enterprise.
It became a library of legal deposits.
>> This meant that a copy of every book
published in England had to be deposited
in the library. A great way to boost
your collection, but a massive headache
for the future.
>> One of the architectural highlights of
Thomas Bodley's original building is the
Tower of the Orders. And five stories up
on the top floor of this Tudor
skyscraper are the records relating to
the Bodleian art collection.
I've ordered up some documents that I
hope might cast some light on the
process by which the Bodleian came into
possession of the portrait of George
Oakley Aldridge.
>> In the latest catalog, it says that the
picture was given to the university by
Miss Benson of East Retford, sister of
the sitter's widow in 1837.
>> So, his sister-in-law gave the picture
to the university.
>> Correct.
>> Right.
>> In the older catalog, the first
scholarly catalog of the library's
collection of portraits, it says a
little bit more.
>> In the catalog of 1840, this portrait is
said to have been painted
in Italy. It doesn't say by whom.
Well, that's a start.
>> That's an invitation.
Well, this is the actual letter offering
the portrait to the university on behalf
of Miss Benson because she was very old
at that time, so her neighbor was
writing on her behalf.
>> Hey, Miss Benson, an elderly lady
residing in Nottingham so he's disposed
to present a painting of the late Dr.
Aldridge. Well, that's very good of her.
So, we can be absolutely certain we've
got a direct line back to him. We know
that it's certainly of him.
But still, although in this game we
always talk about the importance of
provenance, we don't have an
attribution.
And we'll have to prove it by some other
way.
>> I hope you can.
>> As a first step on our journey to answer
the question of who did paint the
Bodleian Library's portrait of George
Oakley Aldridge, we need to have the
painting cleaned. And that process will
take place at the studio of our picture
restorer, Simon Gillespie.
>> This vehicle is turning left.
>> Caution, masterpiece approaching. Beep
beep beep beep beep.
>> I'm rather at the back of the
masterpiece.
>> Here we go. Let's have a look.
Uh
wow.
Well, look at that. A grubby picture,
but looks really lovely.
>> Mhm. Glad you like it. I know you've
been waiting years for me to bring you
>> A picture that's got original paint on.
>> [laughter]
>> There's some very, very lovely points.
And that fur just jumps out as
somebody who really understood how to
put paint on.
>> Yes.
Should we put him on the easel?
>> Yeah.
We'll do that.
>> Right, light.
>> Yes.
Wow, look at that. That's amazing.
You look at this this depth even in this
with the grime and the dirty varnish.
You can still see into that
into the sockets.
This is this is really good.
>> It's going to sing like a choir of
angels once you finish with it.
>> [laughter]
>> To tickle the angels' tonsils, Simon
wheels in his trolley of chemical
cocktails.
>> Right. So, this is the beginning of the
process, which is
taking off this
dust that's sitting on the surface here.
>> Library dust.
>> library dust.
Academics aura.
And you can see the soot. There's
There's wood burning stoves and things
all around the city. Soot fires.
And that is soot. You can see that sort
of bright black [__] stuff, which is
everywhere.
Look at this fresh brush strokes down
here. And there's these um
reflections.
>> Well, you're already looking healthier,
isn't he, Arthur?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, he's been eating his apples,
hasn't he?
He had a lovely pasta lunch.
>> Yeah, we've got a very nice condition
painting and already look at that, the
volume in here.
Look at that drink.
So, the next stage is um is to take off
this the yellow varnish, which you can
still see there. You can see how
discolored it is from the white of this
and the
the yellow on the corner on the corner.
>> Mhm.
>> More stubborn than I thought.
Yeah, slowly, slowly. Here she goes.
Look at that.
That yellow varnish nice yellow varnish
has just aged.
And that's been protecting the paint.
>> Fantastic. What a lovely transformation.
>> Yeah, amazing.
And look how good quality the paint is.
>> There seems to be some evidence of over
paint around the mouth.
>> Just going to see if that comes off.
>> But Simon's initial investigation
suggests a clean and the removal of the
old varnish will reveal a fine painting
hidden underneath.
>> The crucial thing is that our sitter,
who's called George Oakley Oldridge,
>> Oh, yeah.
>> uh none of his papers link this picture
to Batoni. So, it's all all got to be
connoisseurship.
>> Mhm.
>> And we've got to place him
in Rome, of course, at the right age.
So, we've got a bit of work to do yet.
Connoisseurship is the process of
looking at other works by an artist and
making comparisons of style and
technique to decide who painted a
picture.
The next step on my quest to connect
George and Pompeo Batoni is to compare
our picture with a 100% bonafide Batoni
at the National Portrait Gallery.
And I've asked 18th century paintings
expert Professor Robin Simon to tell me
what I should be looking for.
>> Wonderful picture.
>> This is Lord North, later to become
Britain's Prime Minister. And the
portrait was painted by Batoni in Rome
in the 1750s, around the same time I
think he painted our man, George Oakley
Aldrich.
>> Brits loved Rome
and they loved Batoni because he had a
sympathy with what made them enjoy Rome
so much. It was such a moment of
release. It was so exciting to get to
Rome. First of all, you could buy
clothes at
at a quarter of the price that you could
in England.
>> Does that explain why so many Batoni
portraits of of grand tour Brits it
looks like they've just raided the fancy
dress box.
>> It's exactly what they've done.
In Rome, first thing they did was head
to the tailor. Next thing they went to
the portrait painter. Lots of letters
home about I've just ordered a wonderful
dress and so on.
>> Unlike gorgeous George, Lord North was
famously unattractive
and was described at the time as looking
like a blind trumpeter.
But in other respects, I'm encouraged to
see very clear similarities to our
painting.
That open mouth look, that sort of
pursed lips. What I find so magical in
this one is
all the musculature around the mouth is
>> It's perfectly done, isn't it?
>> Anatomic precision.
>> Yes, you didn't get this in great
portrait painters.
>> Yeah.
>> And so they're alive and you're you've
put your finger on it here. You This is
one of the Batoni portraits where the
the my the lips are slightly parted and
he's just thinking, which he is, he's
composing a letter. So you can see the
words of the letter going through his
mind almost. And that's an aspect of the
attorney sets him apart.
>> Seeing this picture has been
tremendously encouraging.
The face in particular is painted using
the same beautifully observed detail as
our picture.
And I think the partly open mouth shows
an artist using exactly the same tricks
to bring his sitter to life.
>> When George Oakley Aldrich arrived to
start his degree at Oxford University in
the 1740s,
Bodleian Library status as a library of
legal deposit meant they were beginning
to run out of space on the original
site.
In the middle of the 19th century, the
Bodleian took over the Radcliffe
Library, but the books kept on coming.
And in 1914, the millionth volume was
added to the [music] shelves.
Hemmed in by heritage buildings at the
very heart of the university, the
Bodleian began looking avariciously at
the neighboring streets.
>> In 1931, a row of houses were demolished
here opposite the schools quad on Broad
Street, and the new Bodleian rose in
their place, making room for 5 million
books.
>> Designed by the architect of the
traditional red telephone box, Giles
Gilbert Scott,
the new Bodleian borrowed several
stories but low street level to create
an underground book bunker.
For the first time in a century, there
was plenty of empty space on the
shelves.
But by the end of the 20th century, the
library was receiving a thousand new
books every day.
They finally had to admit there was
nowhere else to put them in Oxford.
>> [music]
>> Could this be the answer?
At a cost of 26 million pounds and
change, this colossal high-tech storage
facility is just outside Swindon.
It's hard to imagine somewhere more of a
contrast to Duke Humfrey's library.
My guide to this labyrinth of literature
is Virginia Llado-Buisan.
>> This is vast.
>> I I like to call it a city of books
because it's almost like walking about
New York with such tall buildings.
>> The challenge they face now is getting
the books into the hands of the students
30 miles away in Oxford.
>> If someone is ordering a book in the
morning, it is very likely that they can
have it in the central Bodleian building
in the afternoon.
>> So, how much space have you got here?
>> We have 153 miles worth of storage, and
we've filled this amount of space with
now 10 and 1/2 million items.
>> And how long until this space is full?
>> Uh we estimate
>> Mhm.
>> that about 12 years
>> Okay.
>> until we need a new building.
>> It's extraordinary to think this all
began 700 years ago with 20 books
chained to a church wall.
>> To understand a painter better, you
don't need to walk a mile in their
shoes, but look at the places they
loved.
And Pompeo Batoni loved Rome.
As a young man, he spent his time
exploring the city and drawing the ruins
of classical antiquity.
If he did paint our picture of George
Oakley Aldridge, we can be sure it
happened here
because having arrived in Rome at the
age of 19,
he never left.
His first commission was the result of a
chance meeting on a rainy morning under
this arcade.
In April 1732, Count Forte Gabrielli
Valetta was crossing the Piazza when he
was caught in a sudden rain shower.
Taking shelter in the arcade, he came
across a young Pompeo Batoni who was
engrossed in making a drawing of an
ancient Roman sculpture. The count was
impressed by what he saw and the two
soon started talking.
Batoni lived nearby
and the two men walked down the hill to
his lodgings
where Count Gabrielli could see some
more of his work.
The meeting was a fortuitous one for
both men. The count saw the raw power in
Batoni's art and he gave him his first
commission that very afternoon.
>> [music]
>> It was an altarpiece for this church,
San Gregorio al Celio
and it quickly got Batoni noticed.
In a very short time, he [music] became
the hottest painter of religious
pictures in Rome
and he soon caught the attention
of the Pope.
The sort of large scale of religious
pictures that he excelled at were
normally among the most prestigious and
well-paid work any artist could ever
aspire to. But to Batoni, it all came so
easily. And at the age of just 34, he
received his first papal commission for
a colossal picture to go here at the
Palazzo Quirinale.
This was the Pope's official residence
in Batoni's time.
And this is the picture he painted.
Christ presenting the keys of heaven to
St. Peter.
But his first commission from the most
important man in town
didn't go smoothly.
You see, Batoni had a bit of a problem.
He was a perfectionist.
Such was his attention to detail that he
struggled to see when his pictures were
finished, and he was reluctant to let
them go out for delivery to the client.
Even when the client was the Pope.
It took him two years to finish his
first papal commission, despite
continual complaints from His Holiness.
But in the end, the picture was a hit,
and more work for the Pope soon
followed.
>> It's fascinating to think that Pompeo
Batoni was studying anatomy in Rome by
looking at antique statues, whilst at
the same time George Oakley Aldrich was
studying anatomy in Oxford by dissecting
human corpses.
This gruesome business was an essential
part of every [music] doctor's training,
but it was a constant challenge for the
university medical schools.
>> Finding somewhere to study anatomy had
never really been a problem. The tricky
issue was finding the dead bodies to cut
up.
There was a widespread belief that
bodies that had been dismembered could
not be resurrected and thus get into
heaven.
But this was not thought to be a problem
for condemned murderers. They were
plainly going to hell anyway.
Public executions took place here, on
the green between the prison and Oxford
Castle, and they were the main source of
dead bodies.
In 1636, Charles I granted a charter
allowing the corpses of any criminals
executed within 21 miles of the city to
be used for dissection.
>> A public hanging always drew a lively
crowd.
But now the families of the condemned
gathered at the foot of the gallows in
competition with the officers of the
university who had come to claim their
cadaver. Both groups waiting for the
last signs of life.
>> Once the body was pronounced dead, it
wasn't unusual to see fights break out
between the university officers and the
families. And this sort of unholy
tug-of-war over the bodies commence.
>> This is Oxford's Museum of the History
of Science.
They have some pretty gruesome-looking
tools of the anatomist's trade.
But it seems dissection was intended to
add a further terror to the murderer's
punishment.
>> To be hanged with his body left
to be publicly anatomized,
that was utter humiliation.
You know, your beloved, whoever it was
who had done let's say killed somebody,
on the dissecting table, cut up by the
surgeons.
People watching,
>> [music]
>> that was utter disgrace.
>> The knowledge gained through human
dissection certainly gave doctors like
George Aldrich a grounding in how the
body worked.
But I wondered if it helped them make
people well.
>> The situation that would be very
advanced, you would know everything
about the what's called the gross
anatomy of the body. The anatomy that
you could actually see, touch, and
handle. You know how the heart function,
the brain, and so.
The thing is, sir, you could do very,
very little to cure a sick person.
You had to be doctor, a a scholar and a
scientist in the lecture theater with
the corpse.
But at the bedside, he was still on the
same level as Sally the village wise
woman.
>> It's clear that the subject of our
picture, Dr. George Aldridge, was more
successful than Sally the village wise
woman.
Because we know from his will that he
died a very wealthy man.
In 1745, George left Oxford with a
degree in medicine.
While in Rome, Batoni's career was going
from one triumph to another.
To really leave their mark on history,
there was one goal every painter would
have aspired to.
To paint an altarpiece for the mother
church of the Catholic faith,
St. Peter's.
In 1746,
Batoni got the call.
This commission was to mark a watershed
in Batoni's career and in a way was
indirectly responsible for our picture
in Oxford.
The priests in charge of the cathedral
altars, the Reverend of the La Fabrica,
wanted Batoni to paint a new version of
a dilapidated altarpiece,
an episode from the Acts of the
Apostles, the fall of Simon Magus.
The picture Batoni painted for them
showed the moment when Simon Magus, a
sorcerer who was able to fly with
demonic help,
is brought down to earth by the prayers
of St. Peter.
Ever the perfectionist, Batoni made
hundreds of preparatory drawings as he
worked out a highly complex composition.
The picture took him nine years to
finish. And although he was paid in
full,
you won't find the picture in here.
9 months after the painting was
delivered, the Reverend of the Fabrica
had a change of heart.
The old painting was suddenly found to
be in a very good state,
and Batoni's [music] new masterpiece
much inferior.
So, what happened?
I think by the time Batoni finished the
picture,
it was actually rather old-fashioned.
It's a powerful work,
but by 1755, when he finally finished
it,
all the Baroque flummery and dramatic
emotional gestures that had been the
stock-in-trade of this kind of painting
for a century
was starting to feel a bit dated.
This rejection marked a dramatic change
in Batoni's career. He turned away from
doing religious pictures, and instead
took up portraiture.
He already had a long list of clients
who keenly admired his ability to
capture a good likeness, and he found it
easier to tickle the vanity of
individuals than to please a committee
of bickering priests.
At the front of the queue were the
British Grand Tourists who were arriving
in Rome in increasing numbers.
>> [music]
>> I'm sure George Oakley Aldridge would
have been one of those Grand Tourists.
It would have been very unusual for a
student from Oxford University like
George not to have completed his
expensive education with a trip to Rome.
The British affection for Rome really
took off in the 18th century, alongside
the discovery of the ruins of Pompeii.
More and more antique statues and
carvings were dug up every [music] year.
Grand Tourists were gripped by a mania
for the remains of the classical past.
Samuel Johnson observed at the time that
all that sets us above savages comes
from the shores of the Mediterranean.
These new discoveries acted like a
magnet to the British upper classes keen
to see what they thought was the origins
of civilization.
By the time the fall of Simon Magus had
been rejected by the priest of St.
Peter's in 1755,
the trickle of visitors from Scotland,
Ireland, and England had turned into a
flood. And Pompeo Batoni was ready to
cash in.
For his new British clients, he began to
develop a type of portrait that was
unmistakably his own.
He appealed to their mania for classical
artifacts by using these objects and
monuments as stage props for his
pictures.
He not only had a knack for making his
sitters look confident, but he made them
look clever, too.
So, what makes a great Batoni portrait?
What were the tricks of his trade? Well,
step one, show your subject in a
suitably grand location. Top of the
list, the Colosseum.
Step two, show off the sitter's clothing
and accessories. If you wanted your
costume to be shown in such detail or
your sword to gleam as never before,
then Batoni was your man.
Step three, the final magic Batoni
ingredient. Place your sitter in a
classical, dramatic, manly, and heroic
pose.
This picture of Colonel William Gordon
is probably the only portrait ever made
to include the Colosseum
and a kilt.
It took so long for Batoni to paint all
the detailed folds in the Huntly tartan
the Colonel is wearing
that he left it behind in the studio
when he returned to Scotland.
The statue is the goddess Roma
and Colonel Gordon is telling us that
the Scots are every bit as knowledgeable
about the classical past as anyone else.
I'm sure the portrait was painted in the
studio but Batoni certainly came here to
sketch the details of the Colosseum.
And I wonder if I can find the exact
spot. Aha.
It must have been less perilous in the
1760s.
It's amazing how realistic it is. It's
not some little doodle of the Colosseum
in the background. This is
brick-for-brick accurate. And of course
that is what people went to Batoni for.
These paintings were the souvenir
selfies of their day.
And for British Grand Tourists like our
man George Oakley Aldridge
an absolute must-have memento.
When in Rome
Having spent the first part of his
career as the best altarpiece painter in
Rome,
Batoni now reinvented himself as the
best portraitist in the city.
He painted everyone from the Holy Roman
Emperor to the Pope.
Add these eminent people to the long
queue of British Grand Tourists like
George Aldridge and you can see why
Batoni became a wealthy man.
The Spanish Steps were the center of the
British community in Rome
and Batoni bought himself an impressive
house nearby.
Situated in the Via Bocca di Leone, the
house had grand living quarters and a
large studio.
He lives in very great style, reported
one English traveler.
You know, the more I learn about Batoni,
the more I admire him. Especially the
way he stuck to his principles. Even
during the heady days of his popularity,
he never abandoned his passion for
perfectionism.
Nor would he do deals on his prices,
either. When one cardinal offered him a
diamond cross for a painting, Batoni
said he already had a draw for the bows,
and it was cash only.
This self-portrait dates from this
period and shows a confident and assured
Batoni with the tools of his trade.
There are some important clues here for
us, too.
He's painted himself in an oval frame,
just like our picture,
and he's wearing a fur-lined red jacket,
almost identical to the one George
Aldrich wears.
I love the little detail, almost hidden,
of a medal hanging by a ribbon inside
his coat.
He wanted us to know he was fated by
royalty.
His grand tour portraits, with their
classical stage dressings, were a
winning formula. And unlike the Baroque
altarpieces that had made him famous,
they were at the cutting edge of
artistic fashion.
Back in London, with a head full of
glorious Batoni pictures, I'm paying a
visit to Simon's studio, where the
careful business removing old varnish
from the portrait of George is ongoing.
>> Welcome to our old friend.
>> Yes.
>> [snorts]
>> He's got a lot of graffiti on him.
>> The little tiny test that we've carried
out to see how feasible it is to take
off over paint and varnish. And those
are the the solvents that we've
different types of solvents mixtures
that we've used. It looks a little bit
alarming, but it's quite a normal
practice.
>> The cleaning is revealing the subtle mix
of many different flesh tones the artist
used to construct the face.
>> This little bit was painted out for some
reason.
I can't quite understand why.
>> What was painted out? The area around
his lip?
>> Around here, yeah. There's a tiny damage
there, but not nothing to
deserve so much over paint.
>> That's interesting.
>> Yes.
>> So, how old do you think our fellow is
here?
>> He's got to be in his 20s, maybe 30.
What do you think?
>> Late 20s, yes. Mid to late 20s.
If this guy was, say, late 20s, then
he's born in 1722. My math is not very
good, but that means the picture would
have been painted around about
>> 50.
>> 1750. Okay, spot on.
Which would make it, incidentally, one
of Batoni's very first
Grand Tour portraits.
>> Is that right?
>> Yeah, yeah. This is cutting-edge stuff.
>> Wow.
Gosh, this is really the seed of what
he's doing throughout Europe, and
everybody who goes to Rome gets himself
painted by Batoni.
>> Indeed, and this would have been
>> one of the first things. Gosh, isn't it
What a fun What a fun thing to have.
>> Well, I wonder if that sort of explains
its modesty, because it's before Batoni
would have got carried away and
sticking, you know, pictures of the
Colosseum in the background.
>> Yes.
>> Absolutely.
Seeing
the technique and everything for the
first time, now that we've actually
taken off all the dirt and varnishes,
always quite a nerve-racking moment, cuz
it's
the first opportunity I've really had to
kind of focus my thoughts on who the
artist is. Does this Does what we're
seeing match up with my
mental image of Batoni. And now that
you've opened up the fur, well,
it seems to me it's good as a signature,
because that just looks like Batoni fur.
>> I don't know anybody else who does fur
like that.
>> No.
>> I mean, how many colors have you got in
there? You've got this white, yellow,
sienna color, dark brown.
>> And of course, Batoni was that
you know, that absolute perfectionist
who was obsessed with detail, and that's
what we've got here.
>> The more we reveal of George, the more I
feel he resembles Batoni's other Grand
Tour paintings.
My next task is to comb the archives and
see if we can find any evidence that
would put George Oakley Aldrich in Rome.
>> However noble they appeared in Batoni's
portraits,
British Grand Tourists had a poor
reputation.
Almost exclusively wealthy, young,
>> [music]
>> male, and usually traveling on chaperone
for the first time in their lives, you
can imagine what they got up to.
>> But I found a Grand Tour story that goes
entirely against the stereotype, and it
involves a really poignant portrait by
Pompeo Batoni.
It's housed here at the Essex Record
Office in Chelmsford.
>> Like the painting of George Aldrich,
this picture is one of Batoni's very
first portraits of British subjects, but
shows a different side to his character.
Thomas Barrett Lennard, later to become
Lord Dacre,
was already in his 30s and married when
he set head for Italy,
and he took his wife with him.
They reached Rome in 1749 and sat for a
portrait by Pompeo Batoni.
>> So, let me introduce you to Thomas
Barrett Lennard, 17th Lord Dacre, his
wife, Anna Maria, and their daughter,
Anna Barbara. The most interesting thing
about the painting is that uh actually
Anna Barbara, their daughter, had died
the year before the painting was made.
>> So, it's made as a memorial to her. He
worked from a portrait that had been
made of Anna Barbara in her lifetime by
the English artist Thomas Hudson.
Uh there's a family story in the records
about uh this this portrait of her being
sent over to Rome specially for Batoni
to work from.
And the reason they were in Rome on the
Grand Tour at all in the first place was
they had gone abroad to try to escape
the terrible grief that they felt they
were feeling about her her death.
>> Absolutely.
>> Oh, that's really heartbreaking. And
actually their expressions are really
the kind of love Lauren and and and
longing and melancholy.
I love the [music] way Batoni has
handled such a sensitive subject.
This was painted in the winter of 1749
and like George Aldrich, Thomas Barrett
Lennard is wearing a fur-lined jacket
which Batoni has painted in his
meticulous way.
>> Presumably the original painting that
this likeness of Barbara Anne is taken
from is still around?
>> We hope it's still out there somewhere.
We don't know. We don't have it here.
>> As a measure of how deeply Thomas felt
the loss of his daughter, he described
her death in a family history. 28 years
later.
>> So, this appendix here, he writes, "This
Anne Barbara, our bitter day, was
snatched away by a violent fever."
>> Her person was such as gained her favor
at first sight.
Her complexion of the finest white and
red.
She was all sweetness and goodness.
She surprised and delighted everyone
that talked with her.
This may be thought a flattering
representation of her, but in truth it
is not.
And therefore, at the hazard of being
thought partial
>> by those who have not known her, I could
not resist the desire I had to pay this
tribute [music]
and this justice to her memory.
>> It's so sad. We can see he really adored
her. The level of detail in her
description.
>> The Dacre portrait shows how well Batoni
responded to a sensitive commission so
early in his career as a portraitist.
But he had an extraordinary run at the
top of his profession.
He was still the first artist summoned
to the Quirinale Palace to paint the new
Pope, Pius VI in 1775,
when he'd been working as a portraitist
for 35 years.
The two men became firm friends.
Pius was a cultured fellow, and it
became Batoni's custom to bring his
latest pictures up the hill to the
Quirinale Palace for a bit of a papal
inspection and a chat before the
paintings were dispatched to the client.
Eventually though, the Pope would have
to make the same journey in the other
direction.
The elderly artist was no longer able to
climb the Spanish Steps to bring his
work to the papal palace.
So remarkably, on the evening of the
15th of October, 1781,
in full pomp and majesty, Pope Pius and
his entourage walked down to the Via
Bocca di Leone to see Batoni's latest
painting in his studio.
In truth, the aging Batoni
>> was beginning to feel the strain. The
painter and pontiff chatted for about an
hour, and on leaving, Batoni was offered
the papal hand to kiss instead of the
customary foot.
It was a singular honor.
>> [music]
>> But in the 1780s, Batoni was in decline.
In the last few years of his life, he
was short of money.
The flow of grand tourists dried up, and
his eyesight was failing.
A friend reported that he was not able
to distinguish between the eyes and nose
of a Madonna he was painting
and had given her six fingers.
He died of a stroke in 1787
at the age of 79.
In his will, Batoni left large sums of
money to his wife and children. But in
fact, there was nothing left to pay the
bequests because he'd been found to have
died in debt.
The ground floor of this house, where
Batoni had been visited by Popes, Kings,
and Emperors, was turned by his
financially destitute family
into a wine bar.
Rome is still full of Batoni's work,
richly animated and vividly colored
paintings in churches and palaces all
over the city.
But his greatest legacy are the
portraits of British travelers,
a potent export that sent the warmth of
Italy to the cold halls and smoky
drawing rooms of Britain.
I'm really fizzing with excitement to
return to Simon's studio and see the
completed restoration of our portrait.
With the remaining varnish and
over-paint removed and the small damages
repaired and retouched, George Oakley
Aldridge is looking splendid.
The obscuring soot and tobacco smoke of
centuries of academic life have been
removed and George has come to life once
more.
>> Oh, it's extraordinary. It just warmth
comes out doesn't it?
>> It
>> a huge amount of the impact is
extraordinary.
>> Really unusual to see.
>> Most surprisingly, the reason for the
later over paint around his mouth is now
clear.
>> Is that Is that a scar?
>> Well, you've got it in one. I think it
must be. I mean, this was all, if you
remember, it was all retouched out. It
was all painted out.
>> It was, wasn't it?
>> Um
>> [music]
>> and so when we started cleaning it, we
thought the fellow there's a damage, but
it's not. It actually looks like scar
tissue.
>> And it You can see that it's very
deliberately worked up. It's This is not
an accidental technique. That's
That's there.
>> Yeah, you have the highlights um from
the from the light coming from the left
and then and the shadows around the
raised scarring.
>> I've never ever seen that in any 18th
century portrait.
Makes sense actually for a doctor,
doesn't it? To um he would be the one
person he might want to show that.
And really who else but Batoni could
pull that off with his attention to
detail?
>> Yeah, it's lovely.
>> It really does feel like there's three
of us here.
You, me, and him.
What a turn up.
>> I'm now absolutely convinced our picture
is by Pompeo Batoni,
but there is still a missing part to our
grand tour jigsaw.
The question of whether George Oakley
Odgers was ever in Rome and if so,
>> [music]
>> when?
If he really is in his late 20s in the
portrait, then he would need to have sat
to Batoni in around 1750.
At the British Library, I've tracked
down some letters which I think might
help us put George in the right place
at the right time.
I've got here the letters of a grand
tourist called Dr. Edward Thomas.
We don't know a great deal about him,
but he was a prolific correspondent. And
his letters are full of information
about who he was seeing on his grand
tour.
In this one here, which is written in
1750,
he writes that he spent a great deal of
time in the company of two English
gentlemen, Mr. Aldridge and Mr. Neal,
friends of Mr. Hearts.
Now, was this Mr. Aldridge our man,
George Oakley Aldridge? Well, I think
so, not least because Aldridge is a
fairly uncommon name. But, more
importantly, we know that these other
people were known to Aldridge, too.
The Mr. Neal, well, our man George
Oakley Aldridge knew many members of the
Neal family. One was with him at Merton
College in Oxford, and another one was a
neighbor who he discusses actually in
his will.
But, I think the clincher is this man
here, Mr. Heart. That's Walter Heart,
who was an Englishman on his grand tour
in Rome, and was also working as a
tutor. And we know that he was friends
with George Oakley Aldridge.
Another one tells us
that George was in Rome with quite a few
quid to spend.
So, the letter says here that uh I had a
most kind offer made me by one Mr.
Aldridge of a place in his coach. As I
cannot afford paying 30 crowns a month
for one of my own to see the palaces and
view the pictures with him. I am now
grown so expert, I can point out a
Guido, my favorite painter, a Titian,
and a Carlo Maratti.
Well, I think this is fairly compelling
evidence. First of all, we can place
Aldridge certainly in Rome, where
Bettoni was working. Secondly, we know
he had money to spend. And third, he was
taking a great interest in fine art. The
most important fact, I think, is that
these letters put Aldridge in Rome in
1750, which is just the date we think
our picture would have been made. In
other words, he's certainly at the scene
of the crime.
With the painting now looking radiant,
it's time to invite our old friend
Professor Robin Simon to cast his expert
eye over it and give us his opinion.
>> So, here we are, Robin. Here's our
potential masterpiece.
>> Well, in technical terms, it's what we
artists would call a corker. It
absolutely hits you, doesn't it,
straight away? It's It's got tremendous
presence.
>> Yes.
>> Robin's attention is immediately drawn
to the scarring.
>> That is very
unusual. I mean, this is extraordinarily
rare because that appears very much to
be a scarring around his mouth.
>> This is what we couldn't understand when
we were cleaning the painting. It was
all covered over with retouching.
>> I bet it was because um
really in the 18th century,
uh to say that paintings of facial
disfigurements are rare doesn't They're
practically unknown. Nobody does it. If
you have one from dueling or something,
you had a black patch or something like
that. But actually just to leave it and
to show it so precisely
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> It's extraordinary. And yet make it such
a compelling image at the same time.
The immediate impression is this is
really must be Batoni.
But has to be a winter picture because
he's wearing furs, and that's one of the
things Batoni never messes up. And
that's always reflected in Batoni's
intensely fashionable portraits. Uh that
that sense of what is right and fitting
at any particular particular moment.
>> Am I right as well that he's
>> He's just a master of producing fur as
well, isn't
>> Oh, yes. I mean, this hat. My word, that
hat. Where did you get that hat? This
lovely studio cap with its little tassel
and so very Italianate. Uh it's a
beautiful thing.
>> But just the observation of how he gets
that three-dimensional
>> Isn't it astonishing?
>> I don't know anybody else who does that.
>> No. No. Do you know, I think especially
hearing you talk about it
so gratifying. I think this might be my
favorite picture we've ever done. Just
think it's a lovely thought.
>> That's quite a claim. Yeah. It's
certainly incredibly compelling. I kind
of feel like
a bond
because of his scar. It kind of reminds
me of my port wine stain, which I never
expose. If I had my portrait done, I'd
probably have it disguised.
As well. So, yeah.
>> That is interesting. Certainly in the
18th century, if I ever have seen a scar
or disfigurement like this on a
painting, it's very much
overstated like like a dueling scar or
something.
>> Absolutely.
>> I don't think I've ever seen a burn or
something like this before. I mean,
normally in this program, we're all
about taking off dirt and over paint
revealing the true intentions of the
artist. But, here it seems to me that
we've revealed the true nature of the
man, the sitter.
Which is
>> That's That's a lovely thought.
>> It's quite
>> That is a lovely thought.
>> It is moving.
>> I would say
yes,
this is by Pompeo Batoni.
>> The confirmation that our painting is by
Pompeo Batoni is cause for celebration.
A lively gathering of students, readers,
and library staff, including paintings
archivist Dana Josephson, assembled in
the scholars' room of the new Bodleian
to hear what we had discovered.
Welcome everybody. Thank you for joining
us here this evening. [music]
>> When the time came to uncover the
restored portrait, we got a suitably
enthusiastic response.
>> [applause]
>> We showed the painting to Professor
Robin Simon, who's a great expert in
British 18th century portraiture.
And he has confirmed that this is indeed
painted
by Pompeo Batoni.
George was looking very distinguished,
and the new attribution makes him one of
the most important pictures in the
Bodleian Library's collection.
>> There's a visible scar that we think is
a burn.
And the decision to include the scar
[music] in the painting is really
something that is not normally ever
seen.
>> Absolutely. I can't stress how unusual
it is to see something like this in an
18th century portrait. In fact, I think
this is
actually unique.
And come and have a closer look.
>> I asked Dana how he felt about the news.
>> Absolutely gorgeous. I love it. It was
so easy to walk past it in for years.
>> It's really come alive, hasn't it?
>> It has. It has. It's It's such an
unusual picture because the man's not
looking at us. He's sort of looking
down, and very modest. And I think he
was quite a self-effacing guy, perhaps
because of that scar.
>> Yeah, I feel that now that it's been
revealed, I want to know even more.
>> It endears him to him somehow. I mean,
lots of Batoni paintings are really
quite sort of pompous and look at me,
and he's not saying look at me, except
in a very modest kind of way.
>> Mhm.